Guide to the E. F. Benson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
E. F. Benson papers
1894-1929
GEN MSS 699
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.13
(8 boxes)
The E. F. Benson Papers consist of writings, correspondence, and business and financial files, documenting Benson's fiction-writing career and spanning the years 1894 to 1929. Writings consist almost entirely of drafts, most corrected, of short stories by Benson, his novel Paul (1906), and an evidently unpublished and untitled novel written in 1906. Among the short stories are two of Benson's most celebrated "spook stories," "The Superannuation Department AD 1945" (1906) and "The Thing in the Hall" (1912). Other papers include correspondence, sales and royalty statements, contracts, bills, and receipts that document Benson's business dealings with his literary agency (the Authors' Syndicate, Ltd.) and various publishers.
Benson, E. F. (Edward Frederic), 1867-1940
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, and the George Henry Nettleton Fund, 1991-1996, and from Julian Nangle on the George Henry Nettleton Fund, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
E. F. Benson, 1867-1940
Edward Frederic Benson was a British author known most widely today for his comic "Mapp and Lucia" series and his short stories of the supernatural. E. F. Benson was the fifth child of Mary Sidgwick Benson and Edward White Benson, who served as Archbishop of Canterbury from 1883 to 1896. Benson was educated at Marlborough College and King's College, Cambridge, where he completed his studies in 1892.
Benson's first novel, Dodo, was published in 1893 and enjoyed significant acclaim and commercial success. Benson went on to a prolific literary career, publishing nearly 100 works including novels, short stories, memoirs, biographies, and other works of non-fiction. Benson also worked as an archaeologist at excavations in Italy, Greece, and Egypt, represented England in international figure skating competitions, and served in the 1930s as the mayor of the town of Rye in East Sussex.
Scope and Contents
The E. F. Benson Papers consist of writings, correspondence, and business and financial files, documenting Benson's fiction-writing career and spanning the years 1894 to 1929. Writings consist almost entirely of drafts, most corrected, of short stories by Benson, his novel Paul (1906), and an evidently unpublished and untitled novel written in 1906. Among the short stories are two of Benson's most celebrated "spook stories," "The Superannuation Department AD 1945" (1906) and "The Thing in the Hall" (1912). Other papers include correspondence, sales and royalty statements, contracts, bills, and receipts that document Benson's business dealings with his literary agency (the Author's Syndicate, Ltd.) and various publishers.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1894-1924. II. Correspondence, 1901-1929. III. Business and Financial Papers, 1902-1918.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Authors, English -- 20th Century; Ghost stories, English; Horror tales, English; Literary agents; Short stories, English -- 19th century; Short stories, English -- 20th Century; Authors; Literary agents; Benson, E. F. (Edward Frederic), 1867-1940; Authors' Syndicate
- Writings, 1894-1924; Series I; 1.26 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title, with some other material arranged at the end of the series.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists chiefly of drafts of writings by E. F. Benson, including 41 short stories, the novel Paul, one untitled and evidently unpublished novel, and a review of "Jérusalem" by Pierre Loti. A large portion of the drafts are corrected in the hand of the author or others. Unless otherwise indicated, all materials are holograph or typescript drafts (original or carbon).
  - "An Afrit in the Sea", 1895 (Box 1)
  - "Arturo's Boat", circa 1907 (Box 1)
  - "Arturo's Boat" (clipping of published copy on newsprint), 1907 (Box 1)
  - "Assunta's Sacrifice", undated (Box 1)
  - "At Stanhope Gate", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Athletic Ideal", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Bachelors", undated (Box 1)
  - "Big Things", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Blackmailer of Park Lane", circa 1920 (Box 1)
  - "The Blotting-Book", circa 1908 (Box 1)
  - "Buntingford Ware", undated (Box 1)
  - "Candlestick", undated (Box 1)
  - "A Creed of Manners", 1894 (Box 1)
  - "Dicky-Bird", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Earthquake: A Dialogue", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Eavesdropper", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Fall of Augusta", undated (Box 1)
  - "Fifteenth Prelude of Chopin", 1903 (Box 1)
  - "The Flower-Garden", undated (Box 1)
  - "Games", undated (Box 1)
  - "Gare du Nord", undated (Box 1)
  - "Guy's Candidate", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Harmonious Blacksmith", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Heroic Georgie" (clipping of published copy on newsprint), 1924 (Box 1)
  - "An Hour in a Farmyard", undated (Box 1)
  - "Jean Marie", undated (Box 1)
  - "Jerusalem" (review of "Jérusalem" by Pierre Loti), undated (Box 1)
  - "Lady Arbuthnot's Sacrifice", undated (Box 1)
  - "Lilac", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Long Gallery"? (fragment), undated (Box 1)
  - "Mount Street", undated (Box 1)
  - "Now Sleeps the Crimson Petal", undated (Box 1)
  - "Otter-catching", undated (Box 1)
  - Paul, 1905; 23 (Box 2)
  - "The Peerage Cure" (galley proofs), undated (Box 3)
  - "Progress of Princess Waldeneck: A Reconciliation", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Simple Life", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Snowstone", undated (Box 3)
  - "A Study in Collective Emotion", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Superannuation Department, A.D. 1945" (carbon typescript and galley proofs), circa 1906 (Box 3)
  - "The Thing in the Hall", circa 1912 (Box 3)
  - "The Tragedy of Bertram Porter (A Warning to Faddists)", undated (Box 3)
  - "Two Generations", undated (Box 3)
  - Manuscript addition to an unknown story, with carbon typescript notes entitled, "Stories for the Screen", undated (Box 3)
  - Untitled novel, 1906; 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Opinion, evidently to a publisher, by Walter de la Mare on E. F. Benson's unpublished sequel to "Dodo" (presumably "Dodo's Daughter," published in 1913). In carbon of typescript signed in type., 1912 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1901-1929; Series II; 1.26 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence of the literary agency, The Authors' Syndicate, Ltd., relating to the writings of E. F. Benson. Correspondents include E. F. Benson, William M. Colles, William Heinemann, and other agents, editors, and publishers. Correspondence consists of holograph and typescript letters (most signed), retained copies of letters in secretarial hands, carbon copies of letters, secretarial notes, and telegrams.
  - 1901-July 1907, 27 (Box 4)
  - August 1907-1913, 28 (Box 5)
  - 1914-1929, 23 (Box 6)
- Business and Financial Papers, 1902-1918; Series III; 0.63 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Publishers' papers arranged alphabetically by publisher, followed by general papers arranged alphabetically by genre.
  The bulk of this series comprises British and American publishers' royalty statements, sales reports, and account records relating to E. F. Benson's works, consisting of printed forms completed in type or manuscript. Additional materials largely relate to the Authors' Syndicate literary agency and include bills (primarily for typing and copying services), contracts with publishers, receipts from publishers, and account statements.
  - Amalgamated Press, 1909-1912 (Box 7)
  - Century Company, 1914-1918 (Box 7)
  - D. Appleton and Company, 1902-1907 (Box 7)
  - Dodd, Mead & Company, 1916 (Box 7)
  - Doubleday, Page & Company, 1908-1916 (Box 7)
  - Empire Trust Company, 1907 (Box 7)
  - G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1904-1910 (Box 7)
  - George Newnes, Limited, 1913-1918 (Box 7)
  - Harper & Brothers, 1904-1917 (Box 7)
  - Hurst & Blackett, 1903-1918; 3 (Box 7)
  - J. P. Lippincott Company, 1904-1917 (Box 7)
  - Methuen & Co., 1903-1917 (Box 7)
  - Ward, Lock, and Co., 1902-1918 (Box 7)
  - William Collins Sons and Co., 1915, 1917 (Box 7)
  - William Heinemann, 1902-1918; 9 (Box 7)
  - Bills, 1902-1908 (Box 8)
  - Contracts, 1902-1913; 2 (Box 8)
  - Debit Slips, 1902-1904 (Box 8)
  - Receipts, 1903-1912 (Box 8)
  - Statements, 1902-1917 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous lists, notes, records, and ephemera., 1907-1913 (Box 8)